Guide to the John Masefield Collection
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
John Masefield collection
1903-1963
GEN MSS 288
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
0.84
(3 boxes)
Contains letters from Masefield to various people, including Florence Hardy (mainly about her husband, Thomas Hardy), Joyce King, Elkin Mathews, and C. K. Ogden; manuscripts of poems by Masefield; photographs of Masefield; and articles about him.
Masefield, John, 1878-1967
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Ongoing collection of documents acquired by gift and purchase from various sources. Type of accession (gift or purchase) and date of acquisition is noted in the box-and-folder list. For further information, consult the appropriate curator.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Box 3 contains Restricted fragile material. Reference surrogates have been substituted in the main files. For further information consult the appropriate curator.
Scope and Contents
This finding aid encompasses accessions of single manuscripts and small groups of manuscripts and other papers, by or pertaining to John Masefield, which the library has chosen to group and list as an artificial collection.
Authors, English -- Archives; Hardy, Florence Emily, 1879-1937; Hardy, Thomas, 1840-1928; King, Joyce; Masefield, John, 1878-1967; Mathews, Elkin, 1851-1921; Ogden, C. K. (Charles Kay), 1889-1957
- I. Letters from John Masefield, 1936 Feb 17
  - TNS to Mrs. George Pierce Baker, Cirencester, [England], 1936 Feb 17 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Scope and Contents
    Gift, 1945.
  - AL to Mr. Christy, Oxford, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - TLS to Mrs. Davies, Abingdon, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 3)
    Removed from: A Macbeth Production by John Masefield (London, 1945). Purchase, 1977.
  - ALS to Mrs. Goode, Cholsey, Berks, 1915 Jun 14 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    Encloses poem, "Creed," holograph. Gift, 1963.
  - ALS to Mr. Gosse, Cholsey, Berks, 1918 May 19 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - 2 ALS to Geoffrey Handley-Taylor, Abingdon, Berks, 1959, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 6)
    Gift, 1959.
  - 6 ALS to Mrs. Thomas Hardy, Boars Hill, Oxford, 1921-28, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 7)
    Most of the letters refer to Thomas Hardy. Gift, 1958.
  - ANS to Mrs. [Oliver] Herford, Lollingdon, Cholsey, Berks, 1916 Jul 28 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    Enclosing a manuscript copy of his poem, "August 1914," with an inscription to the Herfords and an original tail-piece drawing. Purchase, 1937.
  - ALS to President Hamilton Holt of Rollins College, Abingdon, 1949 Feb 7 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    Gift, 1977.
  - 111 ALS and 7 TLS to Joyce King, 1951-62, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 10-15)
    Accompanied by two holograph poems by Masefield; one holograph poem possibly by Masefield; holograph notes for the Malvern Festival; typescript of an article about King; two photographs of King; and one photograph of Masefield inscribed to King, 1952 Nov 15. Purchase, 1973.
  - ALS to Mr. Marsh, Lollingdon, Cholsey, Berks, 1916 Jul 7 (Box 1, Folder 16)
    Accompanied by ALS to Mrs. Marsh, Congress Hotel and Annex, Chicago, 1918 Apr 10. Purchase, 1956.
  - APcS to Elkin Mathews, 30, Maida Hill West, W., 1910 Jun 23 (Box 1, Folder 17)
    Removed from: Ballads and Poems by John Masefield (1910).
  - ALS to Elkin Mathews, 18 Porter Place, W. (Box 1, Folder 18)
    Enclosing "A June Twilight" and "Midsummer Night," holograph poems. Accompanied by holograph note by Masefield; and clipping of "Roadways" and "To the Spring Flowers." Gift, 1992.
  - ALS to Lady Mary Murray, Cholsey, Berks, 1916 Apr 27 (Box 1, Folder 19)
    Removed from: The Battle of the Somme by John Masefield (London: William Heinemann, 1919).
  - ALS to Mr. Neilson, Hill Crest, Boar's Hill, Oxford, 1922 Mar 31 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - ALS to [M. Moyca] Newell, Abingdon, [1953] (Box 1, Folder 21)
    Removed from: The Conway by John Masefield (London, 1953). Gift, 1962.
  - 3 ALS and 1 APcS to C. K. Ogden, 1917-20 (Box 1, Folder 22)
    Purchase, 1976.
  - LS to F. C. Owlett in an unidentified hand, [1930 Oct 11] (Box 1, Folder 23)
    Gift, 1943.
  - ANS to William Lyon Phelps, New York City, 1916 Feb 28 (Box 1, Folder 24)
    Removed from: Sonnets by John Masefield (New York, 1916). Accompanied by an article, including portrait of John Masefield, written by Edward Alden Jewell, which appeared in the New York Tribune, 1916 Jan 23. Gift, 1943.
  - 21 ALS and 3 Christmas cards to Mrs. Edward Bliss Reed, 1916-63, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 25-27)
    To Elizabeth Reed. Accompanied by photograph of Masefield in army uniform. Gift, 1965.
  - 2 ALS to William T. Reed, 1916, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 28)
    Accompanied by manuscript leaf containing the private code used by Masefield and Reed. Gift, 1965.
  - ALS to Sir William Watson, Oxford, 1930 Dec 2 (Box 1, Folder 29)
    With envelope. Purchase, 1948.
  - ALS to an unidentified recipient, London, 1916 Dec 18 (Box 1, Folder 30)
    Gift, 1938.
  - ALS to "Dear sir," Hill Crest, Boar's Hill, Oxford, 1921 Jan 2 (Box 1, Folder 31)
    Removed from: The Widow in the Bye Street (London, 1912).
  - ALS to "Dear Jasper," Boar's Hill, Oxford, Dec 28 (Box 1, Folder 32)
    Removed from: Salt-Water Ballads by John Masefield (London: Grant Richards, 1902).
- Writings of John Masefield, n.d.; Series II
  - [The gods have put this sorrow upon our souls...], n.d. (Box 1, Folder 33)
    Poem, holograph. Gift, 1994.
  - "Ships", 1912 (Box 1, Folder 34)
    Corrected galley proof of poem. Purchase, 1942.
  - "Sonnet", n.d. (Box 1, Folder 35)
    Printed version. Gift, 1994.
  - [We fought in the grass [and] the uplands the whole of a summer's day...] (Box 1, Folder 36)
- Other, n.d.; Series III
  - Color photograph of Sir John Lavery's portrait of Masefield, done around 1937 (Box 1, Folder 37)
    Original portrait is the property of Mr. Corliss Lamont, New York City. Gift.
  - "John Masefield, O.M. The Queen's Poet Laureate: A Bibliography and Eighty- First Birthday Tribute" compiled by Geoffrey Handley-Taylor (Box 1, Folder 38)
    Printed prospectus. Accompanied by clipping. Gift, 1994.
  - "Mr. John Masefield" by Ashley Gibson, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 39)
    Galley proof, corrected. Gift, 1994.
  - Portrait of Masefield, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 40)
    Signed by Masefield. Gift, 1944.
  - Printed version of manuscript sheet music composed by Rolanda Ronal for Mansfield's poem, "A Hundred Years Ago" (Box 1, Folder 40)
  - Signature, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 41)
    Second page of letter inscribed "With all best wishes to you." Removed from: Good Friday and Other Poems (New York: Macmillan, 1916). Gift, 1962.
  - Manuscript leaf containing the private code used by Masefield and William Reed (Box 2, Folder 42)
    Framed. Gift, 1965.
- Restricted Fragile Papers
  Conditions Governing Access
  Box 3 contains Restricted fragile material. Reference surrogates have been substituted in the main files. For further information consult the appropriate curator.
  - Box 1, folder 21 (Box 3, Folder 44)
  - Box 1, folder 24 (Box 3, Folder 45)
  - Box 1, folder 38 (Box 3, Folder 46)
  - Box 1, folder 39 (Box 3, Folder 47)